DAVID C. PETTY **EDUCATOR / ENGINEER**



Experienced and creative engineer and educator with over a decade each in software engineering for technology startups and in computing education for public high schools. Exceptional record of product development and engineering management in real-time embedded systems, telephony, and automatic speech recognition — including as cofounder of two telecommunications companies. Inspiring teacher and mentor to over 2,000 students, focusing on openended problem solving, cross-curricular learning and collaboration, and computing from beginning to advanced; including physical computing and robotics.





WORK EXPERIENCE

Brookline High School

Brookline MA

2018-2023

Teacher

- Licensed Massachusetts Teacher Digital Literacy & Computer Science grade 5-12, Mathematics grade 5-12, Technology / Engineering grade 5-12, General Science grade 1-8.
- Taught AP Computer Science A (Java) CSAwesome (3 years). Taught AP Computer Science Principles Mobile CSP (5 years). Taught Exploring Computer Science (3 years). Taught Java Programming (2 years). Taught WWW Design (2 vears).
- Taught Autonomous Robotics (4 years).

Coach / Mentor

- Coached Botball (3 years).
- Mentored students in entrepreneurship (Technovation Challenge, 4 years and yCITIES mini-hacks, 2 years).
- Maintained website of resources, assignments, and grades.

MIT Playful Journey Lab

Cambridge MA

2019

Summer Journeyer

'Much like a fellowship program, Journeyers [are] members of MIT's newly established Playful Journey Lab, working on a combination of current lab projects and their own independent explorations... to create a community of practice where we build, play, experiment, and innovate in assessment and learning.'

Winchester High School

Winchester MA

2005-2018

Teacher

- Taught various geometry and integrated mathematics courses in grades 9-12 (13 years).
- Taught AP Computer Science A Java (12 years, plus summer school at Phillips Academy Andover). Taught AP Computer Science Principles Mobile CSP (2 years). Taught On-Line Advanced Computer Science (5 years). Taught Exploring Computer Science (1 year).
- Taught Engineering the Future (5 years). Taught Robotics (5 years). Taught WWW design (1 year).

Coordinator

- Held position of Technology / Engineering Coordinator. Had budgetary responsibility and leadership responsibility for five staff. (5 years)
- Held position of STEM Coordinator for Winchester public schools. Promoted STEM teaching and learning K-12 (5 years).

Coach / Mentor

- Coached Winchester Robotics Team, including BotsIQ (5 years), NRL (3 years), Botball (7 years), and USFirst Tech Challenge (1 year). Winchester Robotics Team was 2015 Botball global champions.
- Mentored students in engineering (Real World Design Challenge, 5 years). Winchester RWDC team Flight 01890 was 2014 & 2018 MA state champions.
- Mentored students in entrepreneurship (Technovation Challenge, 4 years, yCITIES mini-hacks, 5 years, and Winchester Entrepreneurship Club, 2 years). Winchester Technovation teams were 2014 & 2015 global finalists (as chronicled in the CODEGIRL documentary film).
- Co-mentored Winchester Computer Science Club (3 years), including ACSL, USACO, and WPI High School Programming competitions.
- Advised students in Winchester Advisory Group program (4 years).
- Maintained website of resources, assignments, and grades.

John M. Tobin School

Cambridge MA

2004-2005

Teacher

- Taught grade 8 mathematics using Connected Mathematics Program; pioneered lesson design and teaching with interactive white board.
- Conducted grade 7 homeroom; taught weekly grade 7 math study skills class; served as advisor to grade 7 students; facilitated weekly buddy groups; was active member of middle-school cluster.
- Developed middle school parent communication database; maintained website of assignments and grades.

SKILLS



embedded systems

HTML5 / CSS3 / JavaScript

continuous integration

entrepreneurship

EDUCATION

University of Massachusetts Lowell

Lowell MA

2011

Masters of Education in Curriculum and Instruction: Mathematics, December, 2011.

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Cambridge MA

1986

Bachelor of Science in Electrical Engineering, June, 1986. Implemented a computer graphics program in PL/I to age facial images for Architecture Machine Group (now called the Media Lab). Thesis titled Explorations in Combinatorial Dynamics, an evaluation of the Novix NC4000 Forth microprocessor for experiments in Information Mechanics. Computer languages studied: LISP, C, PL/I, Pascal, Algol, FORTRAN, and mini and microcomputer assembly languages. Humanities concentration in music.

PROIECTS

dcpetty.github.io

Github pages for depetty.

psb-david-petty.github.io

Github pages for psb-david-petty.

AWARDS

Massachusetts Technology Leadership Council Distinguished Leadership Award.

2014

PATENTS

United States Patent No. 4,447,676. Harris, Jackson, and Petty. Automatic dialer for telephone network access control.

1984/06/08

United States Patent No. 7,003,456. Gillick, et al.. Methods and systems of routing utterances based on confidence estimates.

2006/02/21

AFFILIATIONS

Member of Brookline Educators Union, Massachusetts Teachers Association, and National Education Association.

Member of Computer Science Teachers Association (Co-President of CSTA Greater Boston Chapter, 6 years), National Council of Teachers of Mathematics, International Technology and Engineering Educators Association.

Member of Association for Computing Machinery and member of Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers.

Member of ANS X3J14 technical sub-committee for standardization of the Forth development environment. Also member of Forth Standards Team, precursor to X3J14 and promulgator of FORTH-83. Former Member of Board of Directors of Forth Interest Group. Ten-year participant in Forth Modification Laboratory. Six-year participant in Rochester Forth Conference.

Founding participant in Knowledge Home initiative.

REFERENCES

Available upon request.

Assisted middle-school science teacher with grade 7 & 8 science classes (3 semesters).

EnglishCentral.com Lexington MA 2009

Developed language-modeling software for language-learning website. Held position of *Senior Software Engineer*.

Virtual Research Associates Weston MA 2007-2008

Developed software for ingestion and analysis of wire-service news articles for phase one of Integrated Conflict Early Warning System DARPA program. Held position of *Senior Software Engineer*.

MassBay Consulting, LLC Cambridge MA 2003-

Co-founded consulting company developing embedded software, websites, and mobile apps. Held position of *Managing Director*.

ScanSoft^{©‡} (née Lernout & Hauspie[†] (née Burlington MA 1996–2003 Dragon Systems))

Held position of *Director of Development, AudioMining*[™]. Directed development of ScanSoft's AudioMining[™] product line, including successful semi-annual releases of Dragon MediaIndexer[™] and AudioMining Development System. Was instrumental in transfer of L&H AudioMining assets to ScanSoft. Supervised work of ten developers and co-directed product delivery team.

Held position of *Manager, Telephony Development*. Managed Dragon's efforts in over-the-telephone speech recognition — applying Dragon's dictation engine to short-message-service dictation. Supervised work of four engineers.

Held position of *Senior Telephony Engineer* in Dragon's Portable Products Group. Developed distributed, embedded dictation system. Computer languages used: Python, Java, C++, UML.

- † On 2000/06/07, Dragon was acquired by L&H.
- ‡ On 2001/12/12, L&H was acquired by ScanSoft.
- On 2005/05/09, ScanSoft merged with Nuance.
- On 2022/03/04, Nuance was acquired by Microsoft.

Previous Work Experience Cambridge MA 1980–1996

- During and after undergraduate work at MIT, was a founder of two telecommunications industry start-ups — Telelogic and digiTel.
 - Designed, implemented, and oversaw software for over 400,000
 Telelogic trunk-side autodialers delivered to MCI, Sprint, and the other
 top interexchange carriers. Varied roles included directing engineering,
 providing architecture and product design, developing embedded
 software.
 - For digiTel, and as an independent consultant, worked on telecommunications products for the Norwegian and Swedish PTTs, Siemens, AITRC, and the manufacturer of the Telelogic dialer. Varied roles included directing engineering, managing consultants, and effecting liaison with offshore manufacturing companies in Asia.
- For Ring Medical (which has since become the "nation's largest... medical-only physician answering service," NotifyMD) co-developed company's line of physician-answering-service systems.
- As an independent consultant: developed and distributed software upgrade for trunk-side autodialer Cambridge Software Project, Inc., Cambridge MA; redesigned and maintained answer detection system for Homisco, Inc., Melrose MA; designed and implemented digital electronics and software for Siemens videotex decoder infrared keyboard for digiTel, Inc., Cambridge MA; developed dual cable broadband network tester in conjunction with ASAtech, Inc., Pelham NH; adapted trunk-side autodialer software for combination telephone and cable television service for Twixtel Technologies, Inc., Framingham MA and GEM Electronics, Inc., Chicago IL.